Heat. [music]
[music]
[bell]
[bell and music]
Heat.
[bell]
>> [music]
>> Happy [music]
[music]
birthday.
Heat.
[music]
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome back to the Ask a Bus show.
Today we are going to discuss science.
We're going to discuss space and
everything related to all of these
matters. So I have chosen a number of
questions that you have asked in the
comments and I'm going to take those.
But before we do that, uh let us see who
is there on the live chat. Uh I can see
Shikh Harayan Lag Rahul online. Ashoto
Pande Rahul Kumar M4 J1U Aush Singh
Krishna of the Surinabies Netherlands
Udb Sharma Aayush Yadava once again
Geopolitical Dubai Samrat Shukla Advit
Ashmini Priyanchi Sud conservative 168
Narita Das 3746
um who else do we have? We have Hensy
Penguin.
Uh Abhishek Sonavan,
Adwit once again uh Nabitadas, Mayank
Antil, Surya Prattab, Samrat Shukla,
Abhu Singh, Shri Vata, Rahul Kumar,
Ultimate Power A1,
Hy Penguin once again. Kishor 619, May
Rahul Kumar, real Vladimir Putin is
here, Arian Rocken, Rocking Gaming is
also here, a real painter says glory to
Indra. Uh
to say that uh and everyone else I Ivan
Ivan Roy is also here. Konicha Nirvana
Shanks uh God was alive. Arian Rocking
Gaming Nirvana Shanks Conservative Adwat
Ashwani Balki today Samraat Shukla
Nirvana once again
uh Ankidak is here 7i Atlas is here. S
HSJ09
anand sutrum is here vssvs 2400 namaste
and thank you so much namaste gadwini
and everyone else so let's get going
with the questions what questions do we
have I'll take as many questions as
possible today Manisha karo namaste
everybody else namaste so let's take
some questions let's get going I will uh
I've chosen questions that will
hopefully appeal to and and hopefully
give value to as many people as
possible. So what are the questions? Let
us begin.
Critical thinker says, is the universe
infinite? Universe, is it infinite? And
what is its overall shape or topology?
That's a great question to start with.
Is the universe infinite? What's the
shape of the universe? What's the
topology of the universe? So, let's say
you go out of wherever you are and it's
night time and you look up at the night
sky and you see all the stars and
whatever else you see out there in the
night sky. So, you can you could ask
yourself, is this all there is?
Everything I see in this specific
direction, how far does it go? Does it
go all the way to infinity or does it
stop at a certain certain distance from
where I am? And is there something
beyond it? That's a great question. It's
a fascinating question. It's something
that humans, our ancestors most likely
have been asking since the beginning of
time possibly, right? So, what is the
what's the deal? So, here's what we
know. Look, the universe, as far as we
know, the best understanding that we
have is that the universe began about
13.8 billion years ago. And it expanded
very rapidly in a phase called inflation
which was super lumininal which was
spacetime expanding faster than the
speed of light and then it slowed down
but it's still expanding right now and
the expansion of the of the universe is
accelerating and all the light that
reaches us uh reaches us has had 13.8
billion years to reach us. So whatever
we see, whatever stars, galaxies, etc.
we see, their light has only had a
certain amount of time to reach us. But
it's possible there may be other stars,
galaxies and whatn not that may be
further away, so far away that their
light hasn't had time to reach us yet.
So the universe has been expanding for
13.8 billion years. And
the amount of light that's able to reach
us as of today the that has a radius
let's say from from us a distance of
about uh of about 40 what is it 46 47 or
so billion light years. So it's like we
are in a bubble. We are in a bubble with
us at the center. A spherical bubble and
the diameter is about 93 or 94 billion
light years and the radius is half of
that. So that is the amount of universe
we can actually observe.
Okay, that's how much we can see. But it
that doesn't mean that that's all that
exists in the universe. Most likely
there's way more universe beyond what we
can observe. But it's so far away that
its light hasn't had time to reach us
yet. And maybe not maybe most likely it
will definitely never reach us. Because
now the universe is expanding. Its
expansion is accelerating. And at the
edge of the observable universe, the
expansion of the universe is so fast
that it exceeds light speed. And it's
not breaking the laws of physics because
it is spacetime that's expanding. It's
not light traveling faster than the
speed of light. It's not like that. It's
not matter traveling faster than the
speed of light. Light light. It's
spacetime itself. the fabric of of the
universe itself expanding faster than
the speed of light. Okay. So the
universe that we can observe is has a
diameter of about four 93 94 billion
light years but there is a universe
beyond that that is for sure. So the
question is how large is the actual
universe beyond what we can observe and
what's its shape? What's its topology
like?
So let's talk about shape. We know that
we are immersed in something called
spacetime. The fabric of spacetime. Four
dimensions. It's got three dimensions of
space. Length, breadth, height. And the
fourth dimension is the dimension of
time. Right? But let's talk about the
spatial dimensions. The three dimensions
of space length, breadth, time. So if we
take remember school level geometry, if
you have a flat sheet of paper
and you draw a triangle on this flat
sheet of paper, then the sum of the
angles
adds up to 180°.
But that only works for a flat sheet of
paper. If you have let's say a sphere,
you draw a triangle on a sphere, you
will find that the sum of the angles
adds up to more than 180°,
sorry, 360°, right? So, the sum of the
angles of a triangle on a curved surface
such as this one, a spherical surface
adds up to more than 360°. And this is
what we call positive curvature. So on a
flat sheet of paper you have neutral
curvature. You have no curvature. On a
surface like this you have positive
curvature in which the sum of the angles
adds up to more than 360°. But there is
a third kind kind of curvature which is
called negative curvature which is a
shuttle a saddle like shape. In that you
will find that the sum of the three
angles adds up to less than one 360°. So
three kinds of curvature neutral or zero
curve curvature, positive curvature
which is this and negative curvature
which is a saddle shape. Now the
question is what is the curvature of the
universe? What's the curvature of space
of the the space that we inhabit? And if
you're a cosmologist, you can measure
that by looking at various spots in the
uh afterlow of the big bang which is the
cosmic microwave microwave background
radiation. So you can look at various
spots in the CMBBR and you can based on
that calculate what is the curvature of
space.
Now what we find is that the curvature
of space of our universe seems to be
very close to zero.
It's very close to zero, which means
that the universe is most likely flat.
Now, if the universe is flat, it means
there is no curvature like this, which
means it is there's a high possibility
that the universe could be infinitely
large.
Okay, so that's one possibility. The
other possibility is that to the best of
our calculations, the curvature is
almost zero, but maybe it's not quite
zero. So it could be that the universe
is just gigantic beyond our wildest
imagination. So if we are standing on
the surface of our planet earth, do we
see any curvature? We don't, right? It
seems flat. We see the curvature only
when we zoom out and go at a very high
altitude. That's when we start seeing
the curvature of the surface of a
planet. So maybe it's like that. Maybe
the universe is gigantic, unimaginably
large, and the curvature is negligible
the way we see it.
That's another possibility. Uh so that
is the answer to the shape of the
universe. Maybe the shape is just flat
which means the universe is infinitely
large. Or maybe it's just very slightly
curved which means it is gigantic beyond
anything we can even possibly conceive
or or imagine. Right? And then when it
comes to topology,
topology. So topology is like see the
universe could be flat. Spacetime could
be flat but it could be looped.
So if you if you play computer games,
okay, and you have a let's say a square
screen. Let's say that the game called
Pac-Man. Let's uh let's Google what is
Pac-Man that so that you get an idea of
what I'm talking about. Okay. Pac-Man.
That's a very that's a like a primitive
game 1980s kind of game. Okay. And you
have this this screen over here and uh
and the Pac-Man creature if it goes all
the way to the right and goes beyond the
edge of the screen it reappears from the
left. So it's gone beyond the edge of
the screen from the way we see it and it
reappears from the left. But if you are
Pac-Man then you you might feel that the
universe you inhabit is infinite but
it's actually a looped universe. So that
is another possibility that maybe the
universe is looped. It appears it is
flat but it is still looped. So that
could be its topology. But all of this
what I'm saying right now it's all
speculation. We don't have the data. We
don't have the uh actual u data to back
up any of these specul speculations. But
from a mathematical perspective, it kind
of makes sense that either the universe
is flat and infinite or it is just very
slightly curved, which means it is
gigantic beyond belief or it is flat but
looped which is why it is not infinite
but it is but the curvature is still
zero or flat. And there are ways of
trying to prove or disprove whether it
is flat but looped. So what you do is
you look for repeated pixels in space.
So you see a cluster of let's say stars
and galaxies or whatever in one patch of
space. You try and look for the exact
same cluster or the same other exact
same pattern somewhere else. But thus
far we haven't discovered that.
So at the end of the day the most
accurate physics answer is that we don't
know. The observable universe is finite.
It's got a diameter of about 93 or so
billion light years. the actual universe
is larger than that. It appears to be
flat or very close to flat which could
indicate that it's either infinitely
large or maybe it's in it is flat but it
is looped but we don't have a way of
telling which way it is right now uh
because uh our instruments our methods
of detection etc are still very
primitive. Maybe in the future we'll
have a better understanding of what the
real situation is like. So the
observable universe is finite. The real
infu the real actual universe may or may
not be infinite. We can't say for sure
right now based on our 21st century
understanding the best 21st century
understanding of physics.
Next question.
Adwit says time is not absolute but it's
it's relative according to general
relativity. Then why then when we say
that the universe is 13.8 8 billion
years old. What are we talking about?
Because time is not constant throughout
the universe. What are we talking about?
That's a great question, isn't it?
That's a brilliant question. So, what do
we mean when we say that time is not
absolute? Time is relative according to
general relativity. So, here's the deal.
Time flows, let's say it flows at
different speeds in the universe.
Okay? If you are free floating in empty
space with no gravitational large
gravitating body near you then time will
flow at a certain speed at a certain
rate.
But if you are near let's say a black
hole let's say you are near a black hole
it may not look bumpy like this but it's
the best I could find to a black hole.
So if you are near a black hole the
closer you are to it the slower time
flows
for you. Right now let's say you are
sitting on a rocket on the ground. Then
your time the the the rate at which time
flows for you is the same essentially
almost the same as the time outside the
rocket. But let's say your rocket lifts
off and goes off into space at a very
high velocity. Let's say half of light
speed. Okay, as an example then if you
are sitting inside for you time is the
same as it was before you left.
But if you have a twin brother or sister
on earth that you left behind and let's
say you go on the journey, it takes you
one year to return. You may find that
time has gone forward by several decades
on earth and your twin is like 70 years
older than you are because time flowed
at different rates. For you it slowed
down for your twin. It went it proceeded
as usual.
So the the rate at which your clock
ticks depends on whether you are going
fast or slow and whether you are close
to a gravitating mass or not. So if you
are let's say
living on a planet that's orbiting a
black hole since the time the universe
began then by now maybe for you
only 5 billion years have passed perhaps
as an example. But for us on earth 13.8
billion years billion years have passed.
So you see for them for that alien
species only 5 billion years have passed
since the beginning of the universe. But
for us it's been 13.8 billion years. So
time has flown at different speeds. And
similarly if you're on a rocket as
opposed to not being on a rocket it once
again makes a difference as to how time
flows. So then when time itself is not
absolute when it is relative how have we
decided
or deduced that the universe is 13.8
billion years old that's a great
question. Now you understand hopefully
the context in which we are operating
here.
So see the universe has two interesting
properties.
It is homogeneous and it is isotropic.
What does that mean? It means that when
you zoom out and look at the universe
not at the scale of centimeters or
meters or kilometers or even light
years. When you look at the universe at
the largest scales where galaxies come
together in superclusters and
superclusters come together in filaments
you know scaffold with the scaffolding
of dark matter. When you look out at
that incredibly large scale then the
universe seems to have the exact same
composition in all directions. It's
homogeneous at the largest scales. At
the micro scales, it may be granular. It
may not be homogeneous. But at the
largest zoomed out scales, the universe
is homogeneous. It's also isotropic,
which means that no matter which
direction you look at in the universe,
it seems the same. So, it's homogeneous
and isotropic. And the universe is
mostly empty space. So, let's say that
we and and the and we know that the
universe has been expanding. It's been
expanding ever since it formed. That's
that's the entire thing about the big
bang. It was not an explosion. It was an
expansion of spaceime.
Right? So the expansion of the universe,
the expansion of spaceime is like
imagine you are blowing a balloon that
way. The balloon is the small you blow
air into it and it becomes larger and
larger. And let's say you have got a
bunch of ants on the balloon. In the
beginning they're all together. But as
you as you expand the balloon
any two ants if you look at them the
distance between them increases even
though they are not walking around
they're just sitting there but the
distance between them increases and the
larger the universe gets the more and
more they get apart each any two ants
right so that's the way the universe has
expanded. Now let's say that the moment
the universe began expanding let's say
we put a whole bunch of clocks
in various parts of the universe a very
large number of clocks you see clocks
you see clocks like these we put them we
sprinkle them all across the universe in
parts in regions of the universe where
there is
no major gravitational uh field so far
away from big masses so that the clocks
are not influenced or slowed down by the
presence of a grav of a nearby
gravitating mass. So let's say we
sprinkle
a very large number of such clocks all
across space in the universe and let the
universe expand and let the clocks like
those ants on the balloon drift apart
from each other with the expansion of
spacetime. So the clocks are stationary
in space but spacetime itself is
expanding. So the clocks go further and
further away and they are not influenced
by motion within spacetime which can
influence the rate at which the clock
ticks and they are not not influenced by
the presence of any nearby major massive
gravitating object. So the clocks
they they they run at a speed that is
not influenced by any relativistic
effects and then
see how much time they measure. Right.
And then and and and if you measure the
the the
amount of time that's elapsed at since
the beginning of the universe until the
present day, you will find it's about
13.8 billion years. And obviously we did
not go back to the beginning of the year
of of the universe to the big bang and
sprinkle a gazillion clocks across
spaceime. We did not do that. But that's
the theory. Now, how do we deduce the
way it's actually happened? Well, we
look at various effects and we add all
of them up and we do it in various in a
multiplicity of ways. You know, we
factor in the amount of mass in the
universe, the amount of red shift and so
much whatever else and we add that up
and to the best of our understanding the
universe as far as we know is about 13.8
billion years old based on all those
calculations.
But this is the basic theory behind it.
We sprinkle clocks all across the
universe and measure their proper time
and that gives us the actual age of the
universe. So that's how we know despite
time not being absolute despite time
being relative according to GR that's
why despite that we know that the
universe is 13.8 billion years old based
on this theoretical framework.
Okay. Surya Pratab says what is entropy
in simple terms?
Entropy is an old friend of mine. I've
had lots of very very
interesting arguments, let's say, about
entropy.
Okay, about what is entropy? What is it?
So what is entropy?
If you read a textbook, okay, a basic
physics textbook, it will say entropy is
the measure of disorder of a system.
Okay, what on earth does it mean? Do you
understand what it's trying to tell you?
Entropy is the measure of disorder of a
system. I if you are a beginner
with no background in theoretical
physics, it will make no sense to you.
Entropy is the measure of disorder of
the system of a system. So let me try
and make it more intuitive. Let me try.
Let's say you have a room. I have a
room. I'm in a room here. You can see
all the books behind me are nicely
arranged. There's a nice little
rhinoceros over here. Yeah. Go back,
bro. So, we have this nicely arranged
room that I am in. Okay. Now, let's say
we have another room.
Before we go to the other room, this is
a nicely arranged room. Right now, let's
say I take this rhinoceros and put him
upside down. Will you notice? I think
you will notice very quickly. Let's say
I take these books and disorder them,
you know, put some of pull some of them.
Well, that's disorder. So, let's say I
do that sort of thing. You will notice
the rhino fell down, the books are, you
know, in a placed half-hazardly, some
books have been pulled down and so on.
So, in a very orderly room, a little bit
of disorder, you will notice
immediately.
Now, let's say I have a different room
which is an absolute mess. Let's say
it's a room with bookshelves. There's a
bed. There's sofa
at the furniture. And I have thrown
books on the floor. I've thrown books on
the bed. I've thrown books on the sofa.
I've thrown clothes on the bookshelf.
I've got cables all over the floor. I've
got dust, cobwebs all over the walls,
pens, and stationary strewn everywhere.
And let's say you enter that room and
you will see chaos. You'll see an
absolute mess. You go out of the room
for 2 minutes. In those 2 minutes, I
will rearrange the mess. Make it not
less messy but different kind of mess.
Then you come back after 2 minutes. Will
you notice any change? You will just
notice a mess, right? It's just a mess.
You there's no pattern to it. So even if
I have rearranged the mess and thrown
some books there and some clothes here
and rearranged the cables in a different
messy way, you won't really notice it.
That room with a mess is high entropy.
This room with less mess is low entropy.
So then now that I've explained these
two rooms to you, let me try and explain
what entropy is. Why is one room high
entropy? Why is the other room low
entropy?
A low entropy system like this room is
such that even if you make a small
change in it, you will notice it.
You'll notice something has changed. A
high entropy system is like that
horribly messy room where even if you
mess things around more, you will not be
able to notice that there's been a
change in the mess.
So
a system
in which you can make major
changes without anyone noticing at a
large scale what's happened is a high
entropy system. The more change you can
make without anyone noticing
the the higher the entropy it is.
And in a low entropy system
you will be able to notice a change even
with small change.
Right? So that's kind of an intuitive
explanation of what entropy is. So now
let's let's talk about actual physics.
Let's say you have an ice crystal.
Okay? An ice crystal. It's a very
orderly arrangement of molecules, a a
block of ice, an ice cube. It's a very
orderly arrangement of molecules. It's a
crystalline structure. Ice crystals,
right? So that's a low entropy system. A
small change will be noticeable because
the the the structural integrity of the
of the block will degrade. So if you
have an ice crystal, okay, a block of
ice and you put it in a warm room for
even a minute, you'll start noticing
that that the outer surface becomes
liquid. It starts melting. You'll
immediately notice. So that's a high
entropy system in which a small change
is immediately noticeable or very easily
noticeable. Similarly, if you take that
ice crystal and you put it inside a
glass of water, it will immediately
start dissolving and you'll be able to
see it. So that's a low entropy system
that ice crystal. Uh another example of
low entropy is let's say you have a box
a box in which there is a gas and let's
say for some reason all of the gas
molecules they go and stick to the right
end of the box right side of the box and
everything else is vacuum in the box
then those ice [snorts] those gas
molecules they'll obviously turn liquid
and you will see it
right certainly visible
but that is not sustainable so it'll
immediately go back to gas and you will
see then you will immediately notice the
change. So there a low entropy system
became transformed into a high entropy
system. Now let's say you have a box in
which you which contains a gas and let's
say there are a trillion gas molecules
in there and let's say you shake the box
and rearrange the gas molecules in a
totally different configuration. Will
you notice anything? You will notice
nothing because it's a high entropy
system. Okay. So that that's what we
mean by entropy being the measure of
disorder. So when something changes in
in a system and you can't notice a thing
that's a high entropy system and when
even a small thing changes in a system
but you notice it immediately that's a
low entropy system and nature always
prefers high entropy. So any natural
system typically goes from low entropy
to high entropy from less disorder to
more disorder. That's how it typically
goes. Another way of thinking about it
is that entropy is tied to energy.
Right. So things go from low from from
from a certain configuration of energy
to a different configuration of energy.
For example,
once again that that uh block of ice.
Okay, it's a pretty low energy system
compared to a glass of warm water. When
you have ice at minus3° centigrade and
you have a glass of warm water at let's
say 25° centigrade
that's the glass of water at 25° is a
higher energy system compared to the
block of ice which is at a much lower
temperature. Now if you put the block of
ice in that in that uh glass of water
the temperature very rapidly starts to
equalize right and that's how you see
that the energy is distributed in a
certain way and the entropy rises so
that's entropy and
so like I said the second law of
thermodynamics says that nature always
prefers higher entrop higher entropy
systems the total entropy of a system
will either stay the same or it will
increase it will decrease. That's the
second law of thermodynamics. Now, you
will say, how is it that that possible?
I take water, I put it inside a freezer,
after 30 minutes, I've got ice. So,
hasn't the entropy decreased?
Yeah, the entropy has decreased locally.
But your refrigerator in which you have
a freezer? How does it create the ice?
By sucking out, let's say, the the the
heat from that enclosed space. But it's
it it spews out that heat by increasing
the temperature of the surrounding air
and if you look at the total change
that's happened therm the thermodyammic
change then there's been more disorder
to create a certain amount of order. So
in the freezer the entropy has decreased
but overall the entropy has increased
slightly.
That's how it goes. So that is entropy
in simple terms. It's a statistical
uh measure of things.
A single particle, a fundamental
particle cannot have entropy. It's only
a collection of particles or objects
that can have entropy. That is [snorts]
entropy in simple terms. Hopefully now
this explains what we mean by it's a
measure of disorder. It's the
amount of different ways in which you
can reconfigure a system without anyone
noticing or anyone caring. So let's say
I have a box of partic box of gas
molecules and I shake it around and it's
now a different configuration.
But do you care if the configuration has
changed for you? It's just a gas, right?
It has no noticeable
effect that matters on the world. So
that's a high entropy system. But in
case of a block of ice, it's very easily
noticeable and it changes things
changes. So that in short is what
entropy is.
Next critical thinker says how does
gravity
affect aging or time itself?
Do a person's feet age little bit faster
than the person's face or the person's
head?
Yes. Gravity
and aging and gravity and time. So we
are talking about general relativity
over here. General relativity
is the theory that Einstein came up with
and it's our best theory of gravity to
date. Uh physicists have been trying for
close to a century to find a way to
break this theory to prove it wrong
through exper experimental means.
They've been testing it to its limits
and it's never broken. It's the best
theory that we have experimentally
uh tested theory. So how does general
relativity work? What's the what's the
basis? What what's the basic premise of
general relativity? The basic premise of
general relativity is that the world we
live in is made up of a four we inhabit
a fourdimensional stage. The four
dimensions are length, breadth, height,
the three dimensions we are familiar
with and a fourth dimension which is
time. So time itself is treated as a
dimension in general relativity and
taken together these four dimensions
they form the fourdimensional fabric of
spacetime.
Now according to general relativity
the presence of mass
warps or curves the fabric of spacetime
and the curvature of the fabric of
spacetime tells mass how to move. So if
you have spacetime with no mass in it is
just you could say non-curved you could
say flat and all lines are straight in
that case. But the moment you place a
mass in space time in that
fourdimensional fabric, it all curves
up. It warps and the lines are no longer
straight. So the partic so the mass the
massive object has to travel across
curved
lines and that's why that causes the
effects that we consider to be you know
gravitational effects like the uh orbits
of planets around stars, the orbits of
stars around galaxies and and so on.
Now, so far we're talking about space,
spatial curvature and curved orbits and
curved uh paths that massive objects
take because of the presence of of of
mass.
But this curvature of spaceime is not
just the curvature of space. It's also
also the curvature of time. So time
itself is curved.
Okay, time itself is curved.
So the closer you are to a massive
object, the more you will find time
being curved, curvature of time. And the
further you are from a massive object,
the less you will find time being curved
along with space.
And it is if you do the calculations you
will find that it is the curvature of
time more than the curvature of space
that creates the effect that we consider
to be the force of gravity. Why do we
have weight?
This effect called weight is because of
the curvature of time more than space.
Okay. Now I'll not go into the equations
to explain and prove that.
It is the curvature of time more than
space that causes the the the effect
that we call gravity. Now
the closer like I said the closer you
you are to a mass the slower time flows
and the more time is curved. So if you
are standing if you spend the majority
of your of your life standing then your
feet are closer to the center of our
planet than your head. Let's say you are
an average person 1.7 m tall.
And let's say you live at a to let's say
you live 80 years. Let's say you're 80
years old today. Okay. So if you measure
the time difference
the the see like I said clocks clocks if
I take this clock and I put it on the
surface of the planet it will tick at a
certain rate and it's closer to the the
center of the planet. If I take this
clock and I I put it 1.7 m above the
surface of the planet it will tick
slightly faster very very slightly
faster
and if you measure the dist the
difference over 80 years you will find
that it will be of the order of 1
microcond
that is
almost nothing but it is definitely
measurable. So at the age of 80, if you
have spent most of your time on your
feet, okay, two/irds of the day on the
feet, your head is about a microscond
older
than the feet,
not younger, older. The feet are closer
to the mass, so they age slower. The
head is further from the mass, so it's
age, so it's going to age faster. If you
live most of your life at a at a
altitude of of let's say 3 kilometers
above sea level then you will age
slightly slower than a person who lives
at sea level.
If you are in a spacecraft orbiting the
earth at let's say 200 kilometers above
the surface, you're going to age faster
than a person who is at sea level. So
the higher you go above above the planet
the faster you age and the closer you
are to sea level the slower you age and
this is something that we see that we
have to incorporate in GPS satellites.
So GPS satellites um they travel at a
certain speed around the planet and
they're at a certain height above the
planet. They are typically ge
geostationary
right that's about 36 37,000 kil 36,000
kilometers above sea level.
So because they are so much faster so
much so much higher they will take
faster
than so than somebody who at the at sea
level and the speed at which they're
traveling also makes a difference right
so because it's higher it's ticking
faster but because it's going faster on
the planet it ticks slower so you have
to subtract the two effects from each
other to come up at the to come up with
the exact speed at which the clocks will
take on a GPS satellite and if you don't
incorporate that the time difference
your GPS readings will be off by
kilometers in just a few days. So that's
another proof of the uh validity of
Einstein's theory of general relativity.
So basically that's how gravity affects
aging and the and the passage of time.
The closer you are to the planet or or
the of the or to the center of the
planet, the slower your clock will tick
by a very small amount. And the higher
you are, the faster your clock will tick
and that's why your head is older than
your feet.
Himman Shu Sharma says, "Is time a
fundamental property of the universe or
is it an emergent property that emerges
from something?" Do you think that time
is a basic property of the universe or
something that arises from deeper
physics?
Interesting question.
So what is a fundamental property? What
is an emergent property?
Think about the game of chess.
You play the game of chess. I'm sure
everyone's tried at least some point in
at some point in their life. In the game
of chess, you have all these chess
pieces. And each piece moves in specific
ways, right? The knight will move in a
certain way, two and a half steps. The
bishop will move diagonally. Pawns can
first take two steps or one step, but
they're only one step onwards. And you
can they can annihilate each other only
diagonally and so on. Rooks can walk can
move in a certain way, etc. So these
rules that are part of chess, can you
derive them from first principles? You
can't.
The rules are the game of chess. Right?
So the rules are a fundamental property
of the game of chess. They don't emerge
for from other principles from the chess
board or or whatever. The rules are the
game of the of chess. So the rules are a
fundamental property.
um an emergent property could be
something else something that can be
calculated or something that can be
derived from something more fundamental.
So now when it comes to time
right we are told that the universe we
are not told we have calculated that the
universe is 13.8 billion years old
that's the best uh calculation that's
the best understanding that we have as
of today.
So the question is
we talk about time.
Did time begin
at the moment of the big bang. Was the
moment f of the big bang time t equal to
0 seconds and then time started ticking
ticking let's say forward time t equal
to 1 t equal 2 seconds and so on until
until where we are today. So did time
begin with the big bang itself or is
time something that is a consequence of
something else that is
inherent or fundamental to the
properties of the universe? That's the
big question you're asking which means
that
is is time emergent? Do could you have
perhaps atoms or molecules of time?
Could time be quantum mechanical in
nature? Could there be quanta of time
etc. Right? And was there a time when
there was no time itself? Right? That's
the kind of deep questions we are asking
over here. Now there are certain
certain theories that approach time
differently which could perhaps give us
an answer. So the two best theories that
we have of physics today
are one general relativity and second
quantum mechanics quantum field theory.
General relativity
is the theory of the universe at the at
its large scales and general um and and
quantum mechanics and quantum field
theory is the theory of the universe at
the smallest scales, the quantum scales.
And these two theories, they treat time
very differently.
In general relativity,
time is part of the fabric of the
universe itself.
It's one of the four fundamental
dimensions of the universe. Yeah, the
presence of mass messes around the time.
It curves and warps time, makes it move
faster or slower, etc. But time is still
a fundamental dimension of the universe,
which means that time was there when the
big bang happened because you have you
have four dimensions of the universe and
time is one of those four dimensions. So
according to general relativity which is
one of which is the most rigorously
tested theory that we have time [snorts]
is fundamental according to general
relativity. When it comes to quantum
mechanics, quantum field theory, time is
very different.
Okay.
If you study basic quantum mechanics
starting from you know the beginner
level, let's say you read Griffiths, you
study Griffiths,
what you'll find is that the Schinger
equation has time. It's got a time
parameter t
and various other equations etc. various
other other treatments
um in quantum mechanics have the time
parameter
but
this time parameter is an external
classical parameter.
It's not something that's inherent to
quantum mechanics. It's an external
parameter that we use in quantum
mechanics.
and to say yeah so so according to
quantum mechanics time is non-quantum
and it is a external classical uh
parameter so that once again tells you
that quantum mechanics isn't able to
explain what time is it treats time as a
fundamental external parameter
so once again just like
general relativity quantum mechanics
treats time as kind of a fundamental
parameter
So these two [snorts]
theories the best two theories that we
have they seek they seem to be telling
us that time is fundamental at least to
the best understanding that we have. Now
there is
there is a theory which is not proven
but it's it's this theory which says
that time could be an emergent property
that emerges from
quantum entanglement.
So quantum entanglement is this one of
the weirdness you know one of the weird
uh things that comes out of quantum
mechanics which says that in quantum
entanglement let's say you have two
entangled particles.
It means that these two particles have
properties that are inherently
correlated in a way that that is
non-classical. It's only purely quantum
mechanical which means that the wave fun
they don't have separate wave functions
in more technical language. They have a
single wave function that describes both
the particles.
And no matter where you are, let's say I
have one particle or one yeah one
particle here on Earth and I have
another particle on Mars. If I measure a
specific property of this particle here
on Earth, I will immediately
instantaneously know the corresponding
property of the corresponding particle
on Mars. So there seems to be something
very strange happening, but we we're not
quite 100% sure what that is. But so
according to this theory,
time could be a consequence of quantum
entanglement.
But that's just a theory. We haven't
proven or disproven that thus far. And
when it comes to the arrow of time, see
if you take the equations of classical
physics, Newtonian physics for example,
equations of motion etc. you will see
that they contain the time parameter t
and they work backwards as well as
forwards.
So you can take t in the past, you can
take t in the future and the equations
work just fine,
right? So according to it looks like
time has no direction in Newton in
physics, right? Because you can the
equations work both ways. But from our
experience, time has a direction.
The past is in the past, the future
isn't known yet. So
even though the equations can tell you
about the past and the future equally
well, we can only remember the past. We
can't remember the future, can we?
There this there is this block universe
uh concept [snorts] in general
relativity in which you know the
universe is this four-dimensional block
in which the past present future are all
all have happened at the same time but
we can't access the future for whatever
reason. So what could be the reason why
we can't access the future? We can only
stumble upon it one
one second or whatever at a time. Why is
that? So that could perhaps be because
of entropy.
Yeah, that could be because of entropy
because like we discussed uh when we
discussed entropy, the universe
always moves towards a state of higher
entropy from a state of lower entropy.
So you can break eggs but you can't
spontaneously recombine them. You can
melt a piece of ice in a glass of water
but you can't spontaneously bring the
piece of ice back the the ice cube back.
You can't. Right? So because of [snorts]
any system inexorably
over time moving towards a higher
entropy state that could be the reason
why we have an arrow of time that only
goes in one direction. It doesn't go
backwards. Otherwise we would remember
both past and future at the same time
but we don't. That is most likely
because of entropy.
So coming back to the question is time
fundamental or emergent? Well, general
relativity seems to be saying that time
is fundamental.
Quantum mechanics seems to be saying
that time is fundamental and that's the
best understanding that we have right
now. Beyond that, time is a mystery.
Time is something we only vaguely sense.
We I'm not even sure if other animals
sense time.
Do animals sense time? I mean, we have
experience of animals, dogs, cats. These
are our, you know, animals we are
closely associated with. dogs, cats,
cows, [snorts] uh elephants, these
animals do have memories. They do
recognize people that they've seen in
the past. But do they understand that
there is something called time that is
passing and people age and said we we
don't quite sure if animals have that
sense that time is passing? They have
memories, but we're not quite sure if
they grasp that there is something
called time. It seems that we are most
likely the only species that grasps the
concept of time. there is something
called time and it's passing. But we
ourselves have a very vague uh vague
sense of what time is. So time is
probably one of the biggest mysteries in
physics and uh that's what I can say as
of now.
Rahul Dun says what are the virtual
particles that come into existence in a
vacuum making absolute emptiness of
space a pipe dream. Are those virtual
particles super luminous? Why name why
is this name virtual particles so
ambiguous? Uh they're just mathematics
to give the equ to get the equations to
stabilize
virtual particles. What are these
virtual particles?
You know,
you'll have people telling you that, you
know, in the vacuum of space, you have
particle antiparticle pairs
popping in and out of existence
spontaneously.
And the particle antiparticle pair just
pops into existence spontaneously and
then disappears, recombines, and the net
result is zero. What exactly is the deal
with these virtual particles?
Are these just mathematical
tricks that we use to balance things out
or what exactly is this? So here's the
deal. The best theory of the ultra
microscopic quantum world that we have
is quantum field theory. We have quantum
mechanics. We have quantum field theory.
Quantum field theory comes from second
quantization. I we will not go into all
the details but quantum field theory
says that the the universe is basically
fields.
Fields not particles fields. So we but
what about the particles? We have
electrons.
We have protons. We've got neutrons. We
have quarks. Up down top bottom string
charm. Six generations six six
generations of quarks. We have all kinds
of other particles. We have particles.
Why are you saying there are only
fields? So quantum field theory says
that these particles
are merely localized excitations in the
fields.
So there is a field just one electron
field that permeates the entire universe
and in certain parts of the universe in
certain locations there are excitations
in the fields and those localized
excitations are what we consider to be
particles.
Similarly, similarly there's a single
photon field across the entire universe
and localized excitations
of the photon field are what we
interpret as photons. Similarly for for
the quarks and all the other particles.
So it's just fields fields fields all
across the place all across the universe
and these fields some of these fields
interact some of these don't interact
etc.
So that's the first concept we have to
understand that the universe is actually
made of fields and this is the best
quantum theory that we have quantum
field theory. Okay,
probably one of the most successful
theories of physics that we have. I mean
we explain everything through that and
it really works. So the entire universe
is just fields all these particles etc.
It's just illusion. It's just Maya.
Okay. Now
what if a field in a certain region of
space has zero energy, no energy
whatsoever, absolute zero energy. What
happens? It would mean that there are no
excitations in the field. There are no
localized excitations in the field.
That's what it would mean. But here's
the deal.
In quantum mechanics,
even
the lowest energy state of a field
is not free from what we call quantum
fluctuations.
There is there are still what we call
zero point fluctuations at the lowest
energy state of a field. 0 point energy.
Which means that even when a field has
zero energy, it still has these
persistent vibrations, fluctuations,
whatever you want to call it, it's still
restless,
right? And these zero point quantum
fluctuations,
that is [snorts] what we call virtual
particles.
So you have a localized quantum
fluctuation that can be represented
as a particle antiparticle pair briefly
coming into existence out of vacuum and
recombining before we can offend Mr.
Heisen Dr. Heisenberg
Heisensburg Heisenberg's uncertainty
principle you operate within the bounds
of that you create the particle
antiparticle pair and have it annihilate
in such a small time window that it
doesn't trigger or trip the Heisenberg
uncertainty principle
right so that is the deal so you could
you could consider it to be mathematical
artifacts but it's not just mathematical
artifacts or mathematical uh tricks or
whatever you want to call These zero
point fluctuations, quantum fluctuations
do exist
and there is experimental evidence of
that. The Kazmir effect and whatnot. You
can look at what those things are.
And these quantum fluctuations,
okay, they have always been around. They
were around in the very early universe
when the universe was like this this
size.
So those quantum very early quantum
fluctuations
in that incredibly compressed universe,
what did they end up doing? Those little
quantum fluctuations created over
densities
of matter in very very small areas of
the universe. And when the universe is
so incredibly compressed, a tiny quantum
fluctuation can create a micro black
hole.
Which is why it is highly likely that in
the very early universe you had an over
production of primordial micro
microscopic black holes and in other
eras or epoex of the universe also like
reheating etc. You had possibly uh over
production of prim primordial black
holes micro black holes. So that's what
uh these virtual particles are. Are they
super luminous? They they don't have
luminosity because they disappear before
you can even think of their existence.
But overall they give rise to actual
measurable physical effects. Why are
they called virtual particles? You can
call them whatever you want but that's
what virtual particles are. It's not
just mathematics. It's actual quantum
mechanical effects.
All right
let's talk about black holes. Adwit
Ashmani says what is the no hair theorem
and how is it related to black holes
the no hair theorem. So what is this
hair in the no hair theorem?
The no hair theorem says black holes
have no hair. So when we talk about hair
in this context in physics in black hole
physics, hair is just a slang term
which means
extra details.
What extra details?
When you see a star, when you see the
sun, we know it has mass.
We know it has angular momentum because
it it rotates. Uh it has magnetic
fields. It has uh solar prominences. It
has sunspots.
It has uh uh various other effects. It
it it gives off solar wind. It has all
these little details that together
characterize what the sun is. All these
all kinds of small extra details, right?
But when it comes to black holes, the no
hair theorem says that a black hole when
seen from outside the event horizon has
only three properties. Mass, charge,
angular momentum. Mass,
charge, angular momentum. Everything
else,
the so-called hair isn't there. Just
three properties can completely fully
describe
a black hole's entire set of properties.
everything about black hole mass charge
angular momentum that's all you need to
describe it so that way it has no extra
hair
that's what the no hair theorem means
right and that's how it's related to
black hole so there are look the
simplest black hole
is a black hole that only has mass pure
mass no charge no spin what is angular
momentum spin wait this one yeah this is
more like a black hole so a black hole
if it is rotating around its own axis
like this spinning spinning. So that's a
black hole with spin and a that's a
black hole with angular momentum. So the
simplest black hole is an uncharged
massive black hole that is not spinning.
That's called the Schwarzfield black
hole. Then you also have two other kinds
of black hole. One is a spinning
rotating charged black hole. The other
one is a non-rotating charged black hole
which obviously both these kinds of
black holes have mass.
So that's all it takes to describe the
properties of black holes. Everything
you want need to know about a black hole
these three properties describe it which
is very strange
very strange right because what happens
to all the other little details that go
into a black hole for example
let's say I create a black hole okay
this is a thought experiment I take a
tremendous amount of hydrogen gas and I
compress it together until it becomes a
black hole so I will have a black hole
right which was made of initially just
hydrogen gas. Now let's say I have a
neutron star.
See when a star dies various things can
happen to a star. It can either like our
sun eventually become a red giant and
then the outer layers just blow away
into a big planetary nebula kind of
thing like the cats eye nebula and then
at the core what's left behind is what
what's called a white white dwarf which
over billions or trillions of years will
become a black dwarf. So that's one
possible end of a star. The second
possible thing that can happen to a star
is it becomes a neutron star. The third
possible thing that can happen is it
becomes a black hole.
So if you have a white dwarf, it has a
maximum possible mass 1.44
solar masses which is the Chundra
Shakhar limit. That's the maximum mass
of a white dwarf. Beyond that you will
have neutron stars.
Okay. So a neutron star also has a
maximum limit which is the Tolman
Oenheimer Okov limit.
So that is what 2 point something solar
masses. You can look it up what exactly
what the exact uh figure is.
Let's let's quickly look it up. Tolman
open hyper tool man open
for limit. What is it? two 2.9 or
something solar masses. Over here it
says 2 to three solar masses. I think
it's about 2 2.8 or 2.9 solar masses.
Okay.
So let's say I take a neutron star which
is right at the edge of the limit
right at the edge of the toolman
openheimer folk off limit and I take a
teaspoon of sugar and I dump it into the
neutron neutron star. What's going to
happen? is going to exceed the tool
toolman openheimer folk of limit and the
neutron degeneracy pressure will be
overcome by sheer gravity and it's going
to collapse into a black hole into the
smallest black hole you can stellar mass
black hole you can have which is about
roughly three solar masses
okay so I can create a black hole out of
a neutron star by putting a teaspoon
teaspoon of sugar into it now this
neutron star was complicated it was
complex X. It had an iron plasma
atmosphere maybe 1 mm thick. It had a
crust made of exotic nuclei. It had an
inner structure that was increasingly
more complex as you go in inwards
towards the center. At the near the
center, you'll have nuclear pasta which
we don't even understand properly. All
of this tremendous detail,
it just got squashed into a black hole
and now all the details are gone. All
you have is mass, charge, angular
momentum. And if you take the same
amount of hydrogen gas, one teaspoon of
sugar more than the openheimer to
openheimer fork of limit, and then you
squeeze it into a black hole, you will
have the exact same black hole. Same
mass, same charge, same angular
momentum.
But you form these two through totally
different means,
right? So what happened to all that
fantastic information? the information
about the hydrogen atoms their polar
their their you know the spectra whatnot
and what about all the complex details
of the of the neutron star that became a
black hole all the details disappear
[laughter] so yeah that's the noair
theorem and I'm actually talking about
something else also which is the uh
black hole uh information paradox which
is a totally different matter so anyway
that's the noair theorem a black hole
can only be described by three
parameters
mass, charge, angular momentum,
everything else like the radius is a
factor of these things. The radius of
the swatch shield radius of a black hole
is given by r= 2 mg by c². mg g c^² g is
just Newton's universal constant. So you
have m and c which gives you c is the
speed of light. So mass gives you the
radius. Anyway, mass, charge and angular
momentum.
Ritik P says, "What would happen if a 10
kilometer diameter black hole passed
near Earth's orbit?"
Scary stuff.
Black hole only 10 kilometers in
diameter.
What will happen if it passes near
Earth's orbit in the solar system? Now,
first of all, let's try and calculate
the mass of this black hole. 10 km
diameter, which means 5 km radius,
right? So this black hole which we're
talking about has a 5 kilometer radius.
Let's ask ourselves what is the schwarz
still radius of the sun. Which means if
you take the entire sun you squash it
somehow
and turn it into a black hole. What will
be the radius of the black hole? It
turns out it's about 3 km. Let's roughly
3 km. Let's uh fact check that.
Schwarz shield radius of sun.
Excuse the spelling but it's
approximately 3 km. There we have it. So
if you have a black hole
with 5 km radius,
it's going to have a mass roughly double
the sun
roughly. Okay, let's say it's roughly
twice the mass of the sun. So you have
an object which is twice as massive as
our sun but it's only 10 kilometers in
diameter.
Imagine that how shocking that is.
That's how much mass is compressed into
this object. This black hole. Now let's
say this black hole
tragically enters the solar system and
passes near the earth's orbit. What will
happen?
So what's the earth's sun distance? The
earth's sun distance is called one
astronomical unit. So let's say we have
the sun sitting here. The earth is going
around the earth. The sun at at this
distance and let's say the black hole.
So the earth the earth is here. Okay.
Over here. But the black hole with 10 km
diameter. It comes from here. This
direction passes from here at a distance
of one astronomical unit from the sun.
Okay. From here. And the earth is here.
So it doesn't come right next to the
earth. Earth is here but the black hole
comes from here at the same distance
from the between as the earth and the
sun distance. So when the black hole is
behind the sun as seen from earth
then the earth will experience way more
gravitational pull than what it does. So
what will it do? And this is the best
case scenario
because the earth will suddenly
experience almost double less than
double but let's say double
hypothetically for the sake of argument.
Let's say the earth experiences almost
double the gravitational pull than it
usually does. What it will do is that it
will fling it will it will totally warp
the earth's orbit.
It will elongate the earth's orbit
significantly. It will become way more
eccentric than what it is right now. The
earth has an elliptical orbit, not a
circular orbit around the sun. The
earth's orbit will be warped
significantly.
It will end up having a much more
elongated orbit around the sun. So,
it'll come closer to the sun at the
nearest approach which will fry
the side of the earth that faces the
sun, boil away the atmosphere and
whatnot. Even if that that doesn't
happen after passing near the sun the
earth will go in a very long elongated
orbit maybe all the way to Neptune
Neptune's orbit maybe Pluto's orbit and
that that orbit will take a couple of
hundred years maybe.
So right now one pass around the sun
takes us 365 days. If a black hole comes
and does this this maneuver maybe one
orbit around the earth around the sun
for the earth will now take 200 years.
And most of the time earth will be far
far from the sun which means it will be
frozen solid
minus 150° - 200° for about close to 200
years and then it comes close to the sun
and everything just melts and and burns.
That is the best case scenario. Which
what does it mean? It means the end of
life on earth.
That's the best case scenario.
Now let's say we have the sun here, we
have the earth here and the black hole
comes from here. Maybe maybe the black
hole comes within let's say
um
let's say um 10 million km of the earth.
Let us just quickly fact check what is
one astronomical unit in kilometers. 1
AU in kilometers.
So one astronomical unit is about uh 1.5
* 10 to 8.
Uh 14 150 million km is one astronomical
unit. So instead of 150 million km,
let's say it comes 15 million km from
the earth.
What happens then?
So this is a much more drastic event for
us. Now
what it will do if it comes so close to
the earth is it will exert tremendous
tidal forces on the earth. See we
experience tidal forces in a very gentle
way. We have the earth. We have the moon
going around the earth. And the passage
of the moon wherever it wherever it
passes it exert tidal forces on the
earth which means that the oceans bulge
out. And because of that we have high
tide and low tide in a gentle way on the
planet. Nothing drastic.
But now we have this monstrous black
hole twice as massive as the sun passing
15 million kilometers or onetenth of the
earth's sun distance from the earth.
What will happen?
The oceans will bulge out all the way.
The earth's crust will get distorted.
Tectonic activity,
the earth's crust will distort. It'll
it'll it'll snap. It'll crack. You will
have magma coming out of of the earth.
It's like a million Yellowstone super
volcanoes going off all at once.
Um
the atmosphere could burn or could be
sucked out into space towards the black
hole and uh the earth will once again be
a a lava planet absolutely hellish lava
planet just like it was about 4.5
billion years ago when the earth has had
just formed. So the earth it's its crust
will be broken. All the lava magma will
ooze out. The earth will become
elongated like a like a rugby wall rugby
ball. And once the black hole passes the
earth may re resume its spherical shape
but it will be back to like the
situation when which you had 4 and a
half billion years ago when the earth
had just formed it. It was a hellish
landscape a molten planet. That's what
you will have if the black hole passes
about 15 million kilometers from the
earth. What if the black hole passes the
same distance as the moon from the
earth? Third scenario,
this is when the ro effect comes into
play.
Why does Saturn have rings?
Because
one of Saturn's moons came too close to
Saturn.
And it came so close to Saturn that the
gravitational pull on one side of
Saturn's gravitational pull on one side
of the of the moon's surface was so much
stronger than the other side that the
moon just crumbled and was ripped into
pieces and that's what formed the rings
of sha of Saturn. Shatter Saturn. Now if
a black hole comes within earth moon
distance to the earth it's going to do
that thing to earth. It will simply
shred the earth into spaghetti.
So earth will become a long string of
lava and magma. Some of it will be
sucked into the black hole. So it won't
go straight into the black hole. It will
form an accretion disc like Saturn, a
molten glowing accretion disc which over
months or years or decades will be
completely absorbed by the black hole.
And some of Earth will be left behind.
Some of it will be flung into space
never to return and some of it will be
left behind which may recoales into a
much smaller planet and obviously once
again this is an extinction event
nothing survives. So all three scenarios
life is destroyed on the planet and this
is what we talk about what happens to
the earth right but if a black hole were
to pass through the inner solar system
it will mess up the orbits of all the
planets
and the entire solar system will be
reconfigured drastically. It will be
unimaginably
altered forever if a black hole just
zips through the inner solar system like
threeey atlas or mua mua or whatever
else. It may even
you know hurt the sun. It may even do
something bad to the sun.
So these are the different scenarios
that could uh ensue ensue if a black
hole passes through the inner solar
system reasonably close to the earth's
orbit. pretty scary scenarios and in
none of the scenarios does any life
survive on the planet.
Adashi says we know black holes are
majorly described by three properties
angular momentum charge and mass. But if
a black hole is charged where does it
store this charge? Does it store this
charge on the surface of the black hole
or does it store the charge inside the
black hole? If it's on the surface, then
how is it just empty space on the
outside? Okay, before I begin to answer
what is the surface of a black hole?
Does a black hole have a surface?
Well, the surface that we talk about for
a black hole, it's what we call the
event horizon. It is an imaginary
surface. It's not a physical surface
with flag over there. Hey, you're
passing the event horizon. No such
thing. If you are an astronaut,
an unfortunate astronaut, and you're
falling into a black hole, when you
cross the event horizon, you will feel
no nothing at all, you will feel nothing
special once you cross the event
horizon. You will not even know that you
cross the event horizon. So, it's not a
real surface. It's not a physical
surface that you can touch or feel. It's
not a membrane that you pass through
when you you feel it. It's just
it's just a causal boundary. Once you
cross that invisible imaginary boundary,
there's no way you ever come out. Come
out. That's the event horizon. And
that's the surface of a black hole from
from our intents and purposes from
outside. Okay. Now,
now the question, what is where is where
is the charge of a black hole stored?
Right? Where does where is it where is
it stored? See, let's say I have a ball,
a copper ball which has a let's say net
negative charge. Okay.
So, how do I know this copper ball?
Imagine this is a copper ball. You get
the point. So, how do I know this copper
ball has x amount of negative charge?
How do I know it? Do I open the copper
ball and look inside? How many electrons
are there? Do I count the electrons?
Of course not. I don't count the
electrons.
What you do to measure the charge of a
copper ball is you bring a small test
charge near this copper ball and you
measure the electric field
near the copper ball. That's what you
typically do. That's how you measure the
charge of a copper ball, iron ball,
whatever ball of of any charged object.
That's how you measure its charge.
And the same goes for black holes. Let's
say I have a charged black hole. Let's
say I have a black black hole and I want
to measure the charge. So I could bring
a probe near it and measure the electric
lines of force. I mean, you know, test
do the same thing I would do with a with
a copper ball. You can use Goss' law.
You know, the electric flux coming
through the surface through any gshian
surface is an indicator of how much
charge the surface contains. That sort
of thing.
So based on this understanding
if you are an external observer who is
fortunately not inside the black hole
then from your perspective
the entire charge of the black hole is
present on the surface of the black hole
this imaginary surface called the event
horizon.
So if the black hole has a net charge,
all of that charge is smeared on the
surface of the black hole. The surface
is like a perfect conductor of charge.
Perfect conductor of electricity char.
Yeah,
that's how we see it from outside. But
actually, what's the deal? Well, if you
look at Maxwell's equations, you solve
Maxwell's equations, it'll tell you that
the electrical electric lines of force,
they go all the way inside the black
hole all the way to the singularity.
But does it mean that that's an actual
singularity inside the black hole? And
does it mean that the singularity
contains the charge? Not necessarily. We
don't quite know what's inside the black
hole. This is just what Maxwell's
equations tell us. And Maxwell equations
don't know about black holes. Right? So
from for all intents and purposes,
the charge of a black hole is smeared on
its external boundary, which is this
imaginary boundary called the event
horizon. Now what what if I I I
shoot an electron
or a stream of electrons. Let's say I
shoot a stream of X number of electrons
the black hole. So then the black hole's
charge will increase. It already has
charge Q and I'm going to shoot X
electrons. Each electron has
an electron's charge. So the black
hole's charge eventually should become Q
the original charge plus X * the
electron charge.
So what happens to this extra charge
that goes that arrives at the black
hole. The electrons are going to be
absorbed by the black hole right inside
the event horizon. And yet
the effect is going to be such that all
that charge contained by carried by the
electrons is going to get smeared on the
surface of the black hole.
Right?
So yeah, that's about it. So from an
external observer's perspective, the
charge is going to live on the surface
of the black hole. That's it.
Yajj Noalia says from the perspective of
an outside observer, a black hole never
forms since any object be it the
collapsing star or anything else outside
the black hole should take an infinite
amount of time to reach and constitute
the event horizon. So did LIGO not
actually detect a black hole? And do we
actually not have a picture of a black
hole? Also, black holes supposedly
should evaporate through Hawking
radiation in a finite amount of time. So
from the perspective of an outside
observer, does a black hole evaporate
before it can even form? Interesting
interesting interesting questions.
So
what happens? So first of all, let's do
this thought experiment. I have a black
hole sitting here and I have a poor
unfortunate guy
who is falling towards the black hole.
Okay, space spa astronaut wearing a
spacecraft
wearing a space suit. Sorry. An
astronaut wearing a space suit is
falling towards the black hole and I am
far away watching what's happening. I
can't help him. If I try to help him,
I'll also join join him in his journey.
So I stand outside and I'm just watching
my colleague
drift towards the black hole, get pulled
towards the black hole. So what do I
see? The closer my f my colleague goes
to the black hole,
the slower
he seems to be going
from an external observer's perspective.
The the the infalling astronaut
astronaut goes slower and slower and
slower until he or she essentially
freezes. stops moving just outside the
event horizon and then the image of the
astronaut gets dimmer and dimmer and
dimmer and dimmer and dimmer until it
disappears.
You never see the the the astronaut
enter the event horizon and disappear
inside. The person just the the person
just freezes the image of the person
freezes outside the event horizon and it
then starts getting dimmer and dimmer
and dimmer and eventually disappears.
That's what we see. Why is that? It's
because
of relativistic effects. So it gets
dimmer and dimmer
because the photons get more and more
redshifted because they have to expend
more and more energy to get out of the
gravitational well of the black hole.
And the slower and slower thing is
because of time dilation. So because of
this these effects you will find that
you will never observe anything fall
inside the black hole. But if a star
is collapsing into a black hole, then we
should see the same thing, right? We
should never see the star actually go
beyond go in go within the event
horizon. Which means that if I'm sitting
outside, I should never see a black hole
form ever.
What is the deal?
Right?
See,
you will never see a black hole form
because black holes are invisible.
They're not black. They are not black. A
black hole is not a black object. It's
invisible.
So if a star collapses into a black
hole,
you may see the stars light getting you
know freezing
right outside the event horizon and then
the star will become dimmer and dimmer
and dimmer until the star becomes
invisible which tells you the black hole
has actually formed. Now the reason why
there is this conception this this
misconception
that it takes an infinite amount of time
to form a black hole is because of
a coordinate artifact. See black holes
who discovered the equation who's how
were black holes discovered?
Einstein came up with general relativity
in 1915
and this was in the form of the Einstein
field equations and Einstein thought it
will take several decades before anybody
can solve the equations. But just a few
months later an astronomer named Carl
Schwarzfield who was on the front lines
of the of the first world war in the
trenches
in his free time he solved the equations
and he sent them to Einstein. He died a
few months later sad sadly. So this was
the swatch the Schwarz chill solution of
the Einstein field equations and
that's what gave that told that's what
told us that black holes exist
but the coordinates that Schwarz shield
used to solve the Einstein field
equations which are now called the
Schwarz shield coordinates they contain
two singularities one is the singularity
at the the heart of the black hole the
other singularity is at the event
horizon but that's not a physical
singularity it's a coordinate
singularity if we use Edin Edington and
finlestein coordinates or some other
coordinates the singularity at the event
horizon vanishes so it's just a
mathematical artifact but that gave rise
to the misconception for decades that it
takes an infinite amount of time for a
black hole to form which is not the case
okay so you may see from outside it may
appear to you from outside that a that
something that's falling inside a black
hole never reaches the black hole it
just becomes is invisible eventually
after a very long amount of time. And if
a star is collapsing, it may seem to you
that the star stops colling star stops
colliding right outside the event
horizon phase and then it simply slowly
dims and eventually disappears after a
very long amount of time. But it's just
what you are seeing from outside.
If you have the astronaut falling into
the black hole and he or she is carrying
a clock, the clock will be will be
ticking at absolutely normally for him.
But for you from outside it will look
like his clock the astronaut's clock has
stopped. So it's
it's that's why it's called relativity
because two observers will not agree on
what's happening. Right?
So it does not take an infinite amount
of time for a black hole to collapse.
When a star collapses into a black hole,
it typically takes milliseconds for a
prop for a full star to suddenly
collapse into a black hole. The collapse
happens at at such high speeds that the
they are close to the speed of light. In
milliseconds, the star is gone, winked
out of existence. Maybe a second or two
at most. That's how fast the collapse
happens. Okay. So, black holes. So the
question is
did LIGO? So so black holes exist they
form in real time very short amount of
time and we have a picture of a black
hole. LIGO did actually detect uh
merging black holes etc. Now about black
hole evaporation black hole evaporation
black holes evaporate in a finite amount
of time. There's a certain rate at which
a black hole evaporates which depends on
its mass and temperature. Temperature is
a function of mass. dm by dt is equal to
minus k upon m^²
you can look it up. Yeah, dm by dt is
the rate of change of mass is minus
minus means it's evaporating not plus.
So dm by dt is minus k is a constant
divided by m². So it's inversely
proportional to the square of the mass.
So the larger the mass the slower the
evaporation. The smaller the mass the
the faster the evaporation. Essentially
that's what it is. So black holes
evaporate through Hawking radiation in a
finite amount of time.
So from the perspective of an outside
observer, the black hole evaporates
before it can even form. So like like I
said, black holes do form. They don't
take an infinite amount of time to form.
But let's say a black hole
hypothetically for the sake of argument
takes an infinite amount of time to
form. Then how will it evaporate? How
will it start evaporating before it
becomes a black hole? It can't. A star
is collapsing. Let's say it takes
infinite amount of time for a star to
become a black hole. Then how will the
start be the star begin to evaporate
before it becomes a black hole? It's
impossible, right? Only black holes
evaporate. Stars don't. Only black holes
evaporate. Neutron stars don't, etc. So
I think that doesn't make logical sense.
It has to first become a black hole.
Only then can it evaporate. Otherwise
there can be no evaporation possible.
But the main thing is that this is a
misconception that black holes take an
infinite amount of time to form. They
take milliseconds to form when a star
when when the when the floor when the
bottom falls off below beneath a star
once the electron degeneracy and then
neutron degeneracy pressure collapses
when gravity overcomes these two forces
it's game it's game over takes
milliseconds for a star to become a
black hole.
Suratab says why are all suns made up of
hydrogen?
When you say sun's star where all stars
made of hydrogen these stars will use
whatever is available to them. What is
the most abundant element in the
universe in terms of mass? Hydrogen.
About 75% of the
barionic mass
non black hole mass sorry non dark
matter mass of the universe is hydrogen.
75%.
about 24% probably is helium
and the rest is everything else.
Okay, let's just double check that. What
is the hel hydrogen helium composition
of the universe? What is the hyrogen
and helium
percentage composition of the universe?
Uh, okay. What's it say?
So 75% is hydrogen about 24 25% is
helium. Yeah. By mass uh number of atoms
92% hydrogen 8% helium. So about 75% of
the mass is hydrogen 24% is helium and
1% or less is everything else. Oxygen
lithium carbon nitrogen silicon iron
uranium gold whatever all of that is
less than 1%.
So when that's what the universe gives
you, that's what you use,
right?
So that's the that's the primary reason
why all suns are made of hydrogen. See,
what is a sun? What's a star? It's a
gigantic fusion reaction.
>> [snorts]
>> Uh the universe
when it was formed
initially was was just tremendously
massive uh tremendously dense.
Eventually you had you know protons and
neutrons and electrons buzzing around
but it the universe was still so hot
that they could not combine. There was a
brief amount of time when the universe
was expanding when the universe acted
like a gigantic fusion reactor. Okay,
for a very brief amount of time that's
when you had protons and neutron protons
and electrons coming together and
forming hydrogen nuclei and also
sometimes protons and neutrons coming
together one proton two neutrons to form
helium nuclei and then they would
combine with electrons to form atoms.
But before this process could continue
to heavier elements, the universe became
larger. It expanded and cooled. So the
fusion reaction turned off. So what we
were left with was hydrogen about 75%,
helium 24% or so, a little bit of
lithium and that's about it. So the very
initial stars
which formed because of over because of
you know regions of density in space
which came out of primordial quantum
fluctuations.
The very initial stars only had hydrogen
and helium. So they would these gas
clouds would come together and and and
collapse under their own gravity.
Eventually the mass would be so much and
the pressure would be so much that a
fusion reaction would ignite at the
center and the fusion would be mostly
hydrogen fusing. hydrogen nuclei fusing
into helium nuclei and that that gives
off a tremendous amount of energy which
is why the stars are able to repel the
gravitational pressure and keep keep
burning for billions of years.
Eventually you had multiple generations
of stars. So the initial stars
eventually died some of them went
supernova etc. And that gave rise to
heavier elements
and that's how you had the seeding of
other elements in the universe. Um
so that's why overall stars are mainly
even today made of hydrogen. Our sun is
mostly hydrogen little bit of helium 75%
hydrogen 24 or so% helium and whatever
else is the rest right.
Um and obviously another reason is that
hydrogen the fusion of hydrogen gives
off the most energy you can imagine and
takes the least amount of energy to to
ignite. See hydrogen has just one proton
at the center.
And if if you want to fuse hydrogen into
helium, it takes a certain amount
certain amount of energy. But if you
have more protons and neutrons, etc. in
the center, it takes way more energy to
fuse heavier elements together.
That's is why all fusion reactions in
stars start with hydrogen fusing into
helium. Then you have fusion of helium
and other other heavier elements.
Eventually you will have lithium,
oxygen, lithium, carbon, oxygen,
etc. higher and higher things silicon
and it all ends when the starts when the
star starts fusing
producing iron. Iron is the nuclear ash
that is the death sentence of a star.
Because if you try to fuse iron into
something heavier, it's possible, but
the reaction consumes more energy than
it gives out. Which means it kills the
star, which is why all the iron that we
have here came from the death of stars.
Anyhow, that's why all stars are made of
mainly hydrogen and helium.
Aush Singh says the gas giant planets
they don't don't they have surfaces like
the earth if we were to send a rover to
those planets in those planets where
will it possibly land why don't these
gas giant planets have surfaces while
the earth does have a surface what was
different which created such a beautiful
surface on our mother planet okay gas
giant planets such as Jupiter
and Saturn and you also have ice giant
planets like Uranus and Neptune.
So what's the difference? Gas giant
planets like hydro like uh Jupiter and
Saturn are mainly made of hydrogen and
helium. And ice giants like Uranus and
Neptune, they have water, they have
methane, they have ammonia, they also
have hydrogen. So that's the difference.
Now let's talk about something like
Jupiter or Saturn.
mainly made of hydrogen and helium sim
very similar composition to the sun. So
let's take the example of Jupiter. When
we see an image of Jupiter all those
beautiful bands and clouds and all what
is that? That's the very highest layers
of the atmosphere which is mainly
hydrogen hydrogen gas that's very thin
and very cold.
So let's send a probe inside a
spacecraft. We have started skimming the
surface of not the surface but the very
top layers of the atmosphere which is
what we see in the images all those
beautiful bands and all that that's very
thin very cold then we go deeper into
the atmosphere deeper so then the
atmosphere gets thicker and warmer
eventually as you go deeper you will
have thicker and thicker layers of
hydrogen gas and they get warmer and
warmer and the pressure gets higher and
higher eventually you will reach a level
in the atmosphere of of Jupiter
where the air pressure is similar
to the air pressure on Earth and
temperatures could be possibly similar
and it's all hydrogen.
Go further inside it gets the gas gets
thicker the pressure rises significantly
it gets warmer and warmer and hotter and
hotter. So after one earth atmospheric
pressure you go deeper you will have two
earth two atmospheres three atmospheres
10 20 100 several hundreds thousands of
earth atmospheric pressures eventually
you will reach a a region of the planet
Jupiter
where the hydrogen gas will no longer be
gaseous
will be a supercritical fluid let's call
it liquid hydrogen it will be what is
actually called a superc critical fluid
it is no longer gaseous it
You could think of it as a liquid and
it's really dense. The pressure is
intense, immense and it's really hot.
You go further and further inside
towards the center. Eventually you will
reach a stage or or or or a depth in the
planet where you have metallic hydrogen.
So this is hydrogen at a tremendous
pressure and temperature where the
hydrogen gas now where the hydrogen
atoms taken together behave like a
metal.
They conduct electricity and this is
where Jupiter's tremendously powerful
magnetic field comes from. But here also
you don't have a surface. is just
getting hotter and denser and the
pressure gets higher and higher.
Eventually at the very core you may
perhaps have some rocky aspect which the
which is the rocks and asteroids and
whatever else Jupiter has absorbed
swallowed over the millions and billions
of years and that's about it. It may
perhaps you know there are some theories
that says that uh Jupiter may have an a
carbon
carbon crystal center. What does it mean
diamond center core? It's possible but
we're not for sure. We know we don't
know for sure but that's about it. So
there is no actual surface where you can
stand. If you send a probe inside
Jupiter, okay, a rover or a probe
eventually it will just melt or get
crushed but it will never find a surface
to stand on even all the way to the very
end. So if you want to explore Jupiter
for example, what you can do is you can
send a spacecraft
either on a
final mission which it knows it won't
survive. It will be like a a
meteorological observatory which will
take readings at various depths until as
long as it survives readings and it'll
send back maybe data to the earth
whatever it's able to uh send back.
Another thing we can do is we can send a
spacecraft that is designed like a
like like an airship like a balloon.
Let's say we design the aircraft the the
the
space probe to be able to float in
Jupiter's atmosphere let's say at one
one atmospheric pressure off Earth. So
it will float at that at that height and
it can stay there for years if you
design it right. So that's another way
of doing it. Or you can spend a
spacecraft uh you can send a spacecraft
and have it land on maybe maybe Europa
or one of the Jovian moons from which it
can take observations and data from
Jupiter. So that's what we can do. But
as such Jupiter and the gas giants
whether it's Saturn or whether it's the
ice giants like Neptune or Uranus they
don't have a surface that we can think
of as a surface. See on earth we have a
very clear boundary.
We have land and then we have the air
atmosphere or we have ocean and
atmosphere. Very clear dividing line
on the gas giants and ice giants. We
don't have that. It's just the property
of those. It's just the inherent
property of these planets.
Uh so what is different about earth?
Because we are a rocky planet. We have
so much rock which is how we are
fundamentally different from the ice
giants and the gas giants.
Surya
Pratab says when Mars was a habitable
planet what would have been the
condition of the earth at that time were
dinosaurs roaming on the earth during
that period okay so chronology let's see
the solar system forms
about 4.6 6 billion years before today.
Okay, there was the formation of the
solar system.
Our planet Earth, it formed about 4.56
billion years before today. And when it
formed, it was this hot, hellish molten
lava, molten magma planet, which over
time cooled, solidified, you know, you
had the Hadian epoch and whatnot. Very
different kind of planet it was at the
time.
Mars also formed during a similar time
as the earth similar time period. Now
when was Mars habitable? What do we mean
by habitable?
What we mean by habit habitable is that
Mars had a warm thicker atmosphere than
it has today and it had flowing water on
the surface, rivers, maybe oceans on the
surface
and it had precipitation either in the
form of rain or snow or whatever else.
So that is what we mean by habitability
flowing water thicker atmosphere and
precipitation.
So that's so when was this when when was
it the case that Mars fulfilled these
criteria habitability?
That's between
4 billion years before today and 3
billion years. Roughly 4.1 billion years
before today to three billion years
before today. That is the time window
roughly give or take during which Mars
was habitable.
Okay. So what was the earth like at this
time? The earth was very different 4
billion years ago.
It's earth's atmosphere was tremendously
different. Mainly carbon dioxide and
nitrogen and water vapor and maybe some
other gases. Very little oxygen on Earth
at the time. The earliest unambigu
earliest unambiguous evidence of life on
our planet is from 3.77 billion years
ago. The first bacteria about 3.5
billion years before today on our planet
we had these bacteria that formed mats
and colonies whose fossils still exist.
Stromatolytes they're called. Let us
quickly take a look at what these
strummatites would have looked like on
our planet.
Tromatolytes.
Oopsy lazy. Okay, so what do these
things look like? See, these are the
fossils of these ancient stroytes from
about 3 and a half billion years before
today. We still find them along
coastlines, etc. Stroatalytes, fossils
of the earliest life on Earth,
and it's possible that these were our
ancestors. So 3 and a half billion years
before today on our planet we had these
bacteria and that was the only life on
the planet all microorganisms
microscopic life. That's the time period
when Mars was a habitable planet.
When did the first dinosaurs emerge?
Roughly 250 or 270 million years before
today. Mars was long dead by that time.
Okay. So dinosaurs were not roaming on
the earth during the time when Mars was
habitable. You only had microscopic
unisellular mostly life on our planet at
that time.
[snorts] Adwit Ashwani says why can't we
put more neutrons in a nucleus after a
certain limit? Good question. So
we have something. See what's a nucleus?
Atomic nucleus. It's where you have
protons and neutrons and around the
nucleus you have a cloud of electrons
not in a solar system style but in a
probabilistic smeared out smeared out
manner. Okay. So in the nucleus of
an atom we have protons. The simplest
nucleus let's talk about it first. It's
the hydrogen nucleus. It's a single
proton. Then you have helium which is
two protons, two neutrons.
Yeah. Two protons, two neutrons. That's
a standard helium nucleus.
See protons are positively charged.
They and we know that like charges repel
each other. So if you take two positive
charges, bring them together, they will
repel each other very strongly. So how
do we bring two protons together in a
nucleus? How how how do we make it
happen? How does nature make it happen?
There is something called the strong
nuclear force which is a very powerfully
attractive force.
So that is one factor. You take two
protons together, they they have this
electromagnetic repulsion which is very
strong. But there's also the strong
force attraction which is which
counteracts the electromagnetic
repulsion. And when you bring in neutral
particles like the neutron into this
mix, then the strong force has the
effect of stabilizing the nucleus and
counteracting successfully the
electromagnetic repulsion of the
positively charged protons. So you bring
protons together, but you have to add
neutrons also to have an effective
amount of nuclear attraction from the
strong nuclear force that binds the
nucleus together.
So the more protons you put in the
nucleus, the more neutrons you have to
add to have the nucleus remain or become
stable,
right? So that should mean that you
should be able to add keep adding
protons indefinitely as long as you add
more neutrons. But that doesn't work
out. There is something called the
neutron drip line.
Neutron drip line. So what happens?
First of all, before we discuss the
neutron or nuclear drip line,
this is what happens.
The strong nuclear force is very strong,
but it only acts a very very short
distance. It is a it is a very short
range force.
So it will act very strongly on two
nucleons that is what is the nucleon?
Proton and neutron are called nucleons.
two nucleons together the neut the the
nuclear strong attractive force is very
powerful but the more nucleons you add
at the very edges of the nucleus the
strong force becomes weaker than at the
center okay and eventually if the
nucleus is large enough if you add one
more neutron it will simply drip off
it'll simply drip off and that limit is
called the nuclear drip line or the
neutron drip line let's see what it
looks like It's it's a graph. Okay.
Drip line, neutron drip line. And yeah,
so you have you know stable nuclei in
the drip line etc. Two neutron drip
line, two proton drip line. So there are
these limits in nuclear physics that we
talk about. Okay. So the so one reason
is this that the strong nuclear force
despite being incredibly strong is a
short range force. So if you have a
large nucleus and you keep adding
neutrons to it then eventually the
strong nuclear force becomes not strong
enough. It is no longer strong enough to
to have additional neutrons stick to the
nucleus. They just drip off. That's one.
Number two is something called the pi
exclusion principle.
Now there are various humorous ways of
describing it which I will not do here.
Not the right setting. But [laughter]
the pi the pi explosion principle is the
reason why matter has mass. So it's it's
the reason why matter occupies space.
What does the pi exclusion principle
say? First of all there are two classes
two classes of particles of of of
subatomic particles firmians and bzons.
Firmians
they obey something called firmy derak
statistics and bzzons obey something
called Bose Einstein statistics or Bose
statistics. Protons, neutrons, electrons
are fermons. They obey fermy derac
statistics. What and forget about what
all that is. The powi exclusion
principle says that for fmianons
no two identical firmians can occupy the
same quantum state.
So,
so protons come in two spins. Spin up,
spin down. It's it's like one is off
spin, one is leg spin. All right, that
sort of thing. It's not exactly that,
but let's think of it that way. So,
protons come in these two spins. So, in
any one
quantum state, you can only have a spin
up and spin down proton. You can't have
a third proton in there.
And because of that
there is a limit to the number.
So
it's it's think of think of the atomic
nucleus as a stadium. In the stadium you
have the bottommost cheapest
seats. Then you have a higher level of
seats which are more expensive. Then you
have a higher level is more expensive.
Eventually you have the most expensive
seats.
Initially you want to fill all the
lowest seats, right? So you fill them
up. Then you fill the higher energy
seats. Cost is energy. Higher energy
seats. Then higher energy, higher
energy. Eventually there will be a limit
beyond which if you want to add a proton
or a nucleon, it it it simply becomes
too energetic to remain in the nucleus
essentially. And it it becomes it makes
more sense for the nucleus to kick that
proton out or or a nucleon out than to
keep it within the the the nucleus.
It becomes like this extremely
hyperactive high energy gas that you
don't want. So it just makes sense for
the proton to kick for the for the
nucleus to kick that nucleon out of the
nucleus. Another thing the the nucleus
can do sometimes is it can simply
transform a neutron into a proton
through beta decay. It's a it's a
nuclear process
which involves a weak nuclear force
which is one of the other forces as
opposed to the strong nuclear force. So
if you have too many neutrons it simply
transforms a neutron into a proton and
kicks out an electron.
So eventually there's a limit beyond
which neutrons simply won't fit into a
nucleus and they'll be they'll simply
drip out because of the and that's the
nuclear or neutron drip line. So because
of the short range nature of the strong
nuclear force because of the process of
beta decay which is something the
nucleus does whenever required and
because of the pi exclusion principle
because of these three factors there is
a limit to which you can add neutrons
into a into a nucleus beyond which it
simply won't work.
Rahul Dunak says, "Is there a
possibility of discovering a type of
radiation more energetic than the gamma
rays? Can the electromagnetic spectrum
increase at both ends?" [snorts] Great
question. See, gamma rays are photons.
Radio waves are photons. They are on two
different ends essentially of the
electromagnetic spectrum. But these are
not these are not different species of
spectrum of of of protons of photons.
Gamma rays and radio waves are not
different species of photons. They are
simply photons. We use these tags, these
titles to depict photons
of specific frequency or or energy
ranges.
But it's not like the these are
different kinds of radiation. These are
all photons. Let's take a look at the
photon energy range, shall we?
Photon spectrum. How about that?
Which is the electromagnetic spectrum
actually? But um let's just call it the
photon spectrum. Um let's see the first
one that we have here. So see
so gamma rays are extremely high
frequency
um
photons
high frequency tort wavelength
and they are emitted by high very high
temperature object. Okay,
[cough] excuse me. And at the other end
end of the spectrum, you have radio
waves which are very low frequency
uh photons with very long wavelengths.
So for a radio wave, a typical
wavelength is about 10 to 3 m which is
what 1 kilometer wavelength and the
frequency is about 10 to 4 10,000 cycles
per second. For a gamma ray the typical
wavelength is about 10 to -12 m and the
frequency is about 10 to 20 or more
cycles per second. So these are the two
ends of the electromagnetic spectrum.
But these are not really the ends. You
can definitely have gamma rays that are
more energetic than anything we have
seen before. It's certainly possible
that such gamma rays can be emitted.
Theoretically absolutely possible.
Right? See what is the constraint? What
what is the highest
frequency or energy gamma ray that we
can find that can be detected
theoretically?
The
higher the energy, the higher the
frequency,
the shorter is the wavelength of a gamma
ray. Okay. What is the shortest length
that's that's physically possible in the
universe? It's the plank length. 10 to -
35 m
10 - 35 mters and um and the highest
energy gamma rays are are have a
wavelength of of about - 10 - 12 m. So
there's a tremendous amount of leeway
that we still have. You could have ultra
high energy gamma rays and whatnot. So
the hard limit is the plank length when
it comes to the wavelength. The shorter
the wavelength, the higher the energy,
but it can't go shorter than the plank
length as far as we know from the
understanding of physics that we have.
So that's the highest energy gamma ray
that we can ever detect theoretically.
Doesn't mean it will actually be
possible in the real universe. On the
other end of the spectrum, we have radio
waves which have a wavelength of about
10 to 3 m 1 kilometer. But it's
possible. You can have photons with uh a
wavelength of a light here. Why not?
It's possible.
So what is the hard limit there? The
hard limit
is a photon with a wavelength that is
the size of the observable universe.
That's going to be an extremely low
energy photon, but theoretically
possible. So there we have it. There's
certainly a possibility of of
discovering radiation that's more
energetic than gamma rays and way less
energetic than uh radio waves. Both
sides of the electromagnetic spect
electromagnetic spectrum can be
extended. But what about other types of
radiation? Non electromagnetic radiation
nonphoton radiation. See when a star
goes supernova it emits tremendous
amounts of neutrinos.
So that's one type of radiation. The sun
emits neutrinos. trillions of solar
neutrons are passing through our bodies
every second. That's another type of
radiation. Uh ultra high energy cosmic
rays. The
the the most powerful the most high
energy cosmic ray ever discovered about
until about a decade ago was called the
oh my god particle which was way more
energetic than the most powerful most
energetic gamma rays ever discovered. So
there is that as well and once again
even even gravitational radiation is a
different kind of radiation. So it's
possible that we could discover, you
know, other non- electromagnetic types
of radiation that could be potentially
more energetic than gamma rays. For
sure. Yeah.
Shri Chingish Khan says, "How dangerous
is it for humans to cross the Van Allen
radiation belt?" Okay. What is the first
of all, what what what are the Van Allen
radiation belts? These are two radiation
belts. See the Earth has a magnetic
field. The magnetic field does a great
job of trapping solar radiation thereby
shielding us from the harmful effects of
radiation. And these this solar
radiation is concentrated in two uh
belts around the earth which are called
the van allen belts. Let's take a look
at that
radiation belts.
So these are donut shaped belts.
Essentially there are two of them as you
can see here.
inner one and the outer one
and uh one of these it traps electrons
the other one traps protons.
Now
clearly the radiation here is higher
than what we experience. The radiation
in these belts is higher than what we
experience on the surface of the earth.
The radiation is going to be higher. So
if you spend time in those radiation
belts it's going to have an effect on
you.
So the Apollo astronauts went through
the belts on a single lunar mission. You
would have to go through the belts
twice. Once to going towards the moon,
the second time coming back to Earth. So
we have data from the Apollo missions.
So every time you cross a radiation
belt,
it's like getting a CT scan. That sort
of radiation not going to kill you, not
going to cause cancer, but you don't
want to have it happen every single day.
Right. So the Apollo astronauts they
would obviously there would be a rocket
which had which had shielding aluminum
and water and whatnot and it was part it
was traveling at a significant speed.
The velocity was in excess of the escape
velocity of earth. It went towards the
moon and came back. So two journeys
through the belt and each time the
exposure was about that of a of of a CT
scan. So not terrible.
Uh but if you spend an extended amount,
see if you spend let's say an hour
through the in a belt, you may get about
a CT scans worth of exposure. But if you
spend a week there, it's going to cross
harmful thresholds. So the key is to
spend as little time as possible in
these radiation bels. Get out of there
as soon as possible. If you are an
astronaut in low earth orbit in the
international space station
once again we ensure that the spa
international space station is below and
as far away as the as possible from the
radiation belt so that the exposure is
minimized and yet you're going to have
more exposure than if you were on the
surface of the planet and uh
this CT scan um equivalent radiation
data. It's not just about the the
radiation belt, the Van Allen radiation
belt, but also cosmic rays. So all of
that put together, it's like a CT scan,
one one dose of a CT scan exposure, that
sort of thing.
There are certain satellites that have
to be placed in the Van Allen radiation
belts for whatever reasons. And those
satellites need hardened materials,
hardened electronics without which they
die. And even with all the precautions
that we take, the satellites have a
lower life expectancy than a regular
satellite which is not in the Van Allen
radiation belt. So clearly it's
dangerous.
I remember there was this Russian
spacecraft that was supposed to go to
the moon. I think it was called Phobos
Grunt or something
and that spacecraft
it did not have hardened electronics and
it died in Earth orbit before it could
even start the journey towards Mars. So
yeah, dangerous
um for electronics, for satellites, and
definitely for human beings. Now, what
about human beings going to Mars? That
takes about 8 n months.
We're going to have the astronauts pass
through the Van Allen radiation belts.
Then after that they're out in open
space
and they'll be exposed to solar
radiation, solar wind, coronal mass
ejections
and also
cosmic rays that come from outside the
solar system outside the galaxy at
times. Now that is going to be dangerous
and that could cross over into a
threshold where the the probability of
developing cancer over your lifetime is
is higher than normal.
So such spacecraft will need additional
shielding and additional additional uh
precautions to ensure that humans that
the astronauts don't develop cancer or
don't have a higher risk of developing
cancer. So that is definitely going to
be an issue traveling to a place like
Mars. But going to the moon and coming
back through the van Allen radiation
belts, it's not going to be a very big
issue. Unless you get stuck over there
for whatever reason or unless you are
passing through the van through the
radiation belt and at the same time
you're hit with a solar flare or
something or a solar storm then your
exposure will be higher. So it's it's
complicated. There are all these
different parameters that you have to uh
take into account.
Udit Mahesh says, "Why do many countries
have space stations in the eastern most
coastal regions of their territory like
Shri Harikota for India and Florida for
the United States?" Great question.
See,
we know that the planet Earth rotates
around its own axis. How do we know it?
We have day and night. Can you guess
what's the direction in which the Earth
rotates?
Let me give you a hint. Where does the
sun rise? Which direction? East or west?
It rises in the east. Which means that
the earth is moving in the direction of
the east. It's mo moving from west to
east not east to west. Okay. So we know
that the earth is moving from west to
east. The rotation is in that direction
which is where the sun rises in the
east. Now that we understand that what
is the speed of the rotation? If you are
sitting standing at the equator
the rotational
speed is about what 50 1600
kilometers/s
which is massive
massive
so if you have a space station in Sri
Harikota which is close to the equator
then you're going to have a massive if
then when your rocket takes off it's
already going to have this 1 1600 km/h
boost before it even begins to take off.
So that way you have to spend less fuel
to get this rocket into orbit.
Similarly, if you are at Cape Canaveral,
Cape Kennedy it's called now on the
south coast of Florida
and if you take off from there, it's
going to get this massive boost from
Earth's rotational speed. And the added
advantage is is that if something goes
wrong with the rocket, you can simply
splash the rocket down into the Gulf of
Mexico or in the Bay of Bengal and it's
not going to hit any land. So that's why
India and the US have space launching
centers
on their east coasts near the equator
with the sea to the east. Makes a lot of
sense.
Okay.
Critical thinker says why does fire have
a shadow and what is the physics behind
shadows? First of all, physics behind
shadows.
For a shadow to to occur, you need a
source of light. You need a a surface
where the light will be
incident. And you need something between
the source of light and the surface that
either blocks the light, absorbs the
light, uh
or
um what is it? Reflection.
Reflection absorption refraction or
refracts the light which means it takes
it absorbs the light and and emits it in
a different direction. That way
there's going to be a blockage between
the source of the light and the surface
which will be observed observed in the
form of what we call a shadow. Okay,
that's the basic physics behind shadows.
Now why does fire have a shadow? So what
is fire?
Fire occurs when something burns. Let's
say you have a candle. What is the fuel?
It's the wax. What is the thing that
that that is set on fire? It's the wick.
Now what is fire? This this flame that
we see what is it? What what does it
contain? It contains
contains carbon dioxide. It contains
water vapor. It contains oxygen. It
contains various gases. It contains
carbon particles, soot particles.
It contains various organic compounds
that come from the breakdown
of the wax.
And it contains very high temperature
gases that emit photons, light that we
see in the form of a flame.
And these gases, they go upwards because
they're so hot, which is why a flame
stays upright.
Okay? So that's a flame.
Now, let's say I let's say I have a
flame here. I have a surface here. I've
got a source of light here. And let's
say my source of light is brighter than
this flame. So the light will go this
way. It'll hit the flame and the flame
has different gases at different
temperatures
and these gases etc.
Some some of the gases some of the suit
particles will block some of the photons
and and absorb those photons. Some of
the parts of the flame will
refract the light and make it go in
different directions instead of going
straight through the flame.
And because of the combination of these
factors, not all the light that's
emitted from my source will be incident
on the surface. Some of it will be will
either be absorbed by the suit particles
or will be refracted in other
directions. And because my source of
light is brighter than the flame, you're
going to see a shadow on the surface
where the light is incident. So you're
going to see this area where the light
is fully incident with full brightness.
And there's going to be this shadow of
the flame.
That's how a flame can have a shadow
only if the source of light is brighter
than your flame. If the source of light
is dimmer than the flame, you will not
see a shadow.
Okay. Um
feminist slayer says what is another
dimension in films or anime they when
they said that they have moved to
another dimension does it mean that they
have gone to a different universe or a
different world what is the deal what's
a dimension
what are dimensions see we understand we
perceive dimensions length breadth
height I have this object here it has a
certain length a certain length
a certain breadth and a certain height.
Very small height. Right? So these are
the three dimensions physical dimensions
that we are aware of. What it means?
What what is a single dimension? It's a
place where you can go either forward or
backward. That's all.
A place where you can go forward or
backward. So if I have a sheet of paper
and I draw a line on it, I can only go
forward or backward on the line. But if
I have the whole sheet of paper, then I
can go forward or backward in this
direction. forward and backward in that
direction and whatever other direction.
So that's two dimensions that I have.
But if I have a box in that case I can
go forward and backward in all kinds of
directions all three dimensions.
So that's three dimensions. And then we
have a fourth dimension called time
which in the equations can go backward
and forward but we only perceive one
direction. So those are the four
dimensions we can understand. Now in
films, anime etc. they will say that
there are other dimensions. What is
that? So in spring theory, you have
either 10 dimensions or 11 dimensions.
So these are other directions that you
can go backward and forward in. But
those dimensions are compactified.
They're so small, you can't perceive
them. Let's say you have an ant that's
walking on a very thin wire. If I am
seeing it from 5 m away, I can barely
see the wire and barely see the ant. And
it looks like the ant is walking on a
single dimension.
But if I take a magnifying lens or a
microscope and I see and I observe
what's happening, I will see the ant is
walking on this cylindrical surface and
from the ant's perspective it is a
three-dimensional object. So that's an
extra dimension that the ant perceives
but from where I am I can't perceive it
because it's so small. So similarly in
in in string theory there can be 10 or
11 dimensions apart from the beyond the
four that we perceive and these are all
compactified very tiny microscopic
dimensions which is why we can't
perceive them right. So that's
dimensions. Now there is something
called brain world theory
brain cosmology. In brain cosmology what
it essentially says is that our universe
is a fourdimensional
surface on a higher dimensional bulk. So
the higher dimensional bulk may have
more dimensions than the four dimensions
we perceive and observe and
and the universe is simply a
fourdimensional projection of that multi
of that higher dimensional bulk and
there could be other
membranes or brains like upper universe
on the same bulk which would be other
universes. So that's another So in brain
brain world theory brain cosmology you
could have other universes
that inhabit the same bulk that we
inhabit but are separate parallel
universes. So that's different
dimensions you could say from that you
know
pop culture perspective but in films
anime etc they say when they say another
dimension they mean another universe
that's just a lay person's way of
simplifying things to make it
interesting it doesn't in a film
anything's possible right it's it's a
mix of it's a blend of science fiction
and fantasy so you can make up any story
you can make up any rules as long as the
rules are consistent the story is
interesting
Okay. Um, let's take one or two more
questions because we have gone way past
two hours. Critical thinker says, "Can a
star turn into a planet? Why is Jupiter
called a failed star?"
So, let us define what is a star and
what's a planet.
Okay, a star is a gigantic fusion
reaction. It's a gigantic collection
of hydrogen and helium that is typically
hydrogen and helium that is so massive
and self-gravitating that the combined
pressure of the atoms is so high that at
the very core of this collection of
atoms the temperatures and pressures are
so high that they ignite the fusion of
hydrogen into helium.
And this fusion reaction it pushes back
against the gravitational
crush of the collection of atoms. And
that's why the star becomes spherical
and it burns for billions of years. So
that's a star typically hydrogen and
helium with trace amounts of other
elements. That is a star. What is a
planet? A planet is a byproduct of the
formation of a star. So how does a star
form? You have a huge collection of gas
mainly hydrogen helium that starts
self-gravitating that starts coaling
coallesing towards the center and
through because of the motion it starts
it becomes a disc and the disc has a
rotation
and at the center the star ignites and
whatever is left around the star out of
the original disc all of that clumps
into planets. So planets are byproducts
of the formation of a star. Planets can
be rocky or gaseous. Rocky planets are
Earth, Mars, Venus and Mercury. Gaseous
planets are Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus,
Neptune. These are examples.
So stars are very different from from
planets. Stars cannot become planets.
Now why is Jupiter called a failed star?
I don't know who calls Jupiter a failed
star. I think it's just popular. It's a
popular way of talking about Jupiter.
But Jupiter is a very successful planet
actually. It's a very successful planet.
Why is it a failed star? Let me explain
why some people call it a failed star.
It's because Jupiter has the same
composition as the sun. Hydrogen and
helium mostly. So, it's the same
composition of sun as as the sun. The
sun is an active star. It's shining.
It's fusing hydrogen into helium. But
Jupiter hasn't been able to do that. So,
that's why some people call it a failed
star. Now, here's the deal. Jupiter is a
very successful planet but and it's not
a failed star. What does it take for
something like Jupiter to become a star
and ignite fusion?
You need a mass of about 75 to 80
Jupiters taken together for the gravity
to be enough to ignite fusion within. So
the smallest proper stars have a mass of
about 75 to 80 Jupiters.
So if I take a Jupiter and I take 75 or
80 other Jupiters and I bring them all
together then the combined planet will
turn into a star because nuclear fusion
will will ignite.
There's another limit 13 Jupiters. If
you bring 13 Jupiters together
then dutarium fusion begins for a while
and then stops. So that sort of object
is called a brown dwarf. A brown dwarf
is a failed star. There is some fusion
for a while and then it stops. Okay. So
Jupiter mass to 13 Jupiter masses you
just have a planet. 13 Jupiter masses to
about 75 80 Jupiter masses you have a
brown dwarf which is a failed star and
80 Jupiter masses onwards you have
proper stars. That is the deal. So
Jupiter isn't really a failed star. It's
it's a very successful planet and a very
beautiful one at that. Okay,
let's take one more question.
This is by Mary Kane. Mary Kane. In
1945, nearly 16,000 girls or women from
India, the UK and the US
WR IS etc. worked together cerebreaking
using skills like pattern recognition,
memory and mathematics to bring to help
bring an end to the second world war
later remaining under secrecy laws for
decades. The youngest girl would then
would be about 95 to 100 years today.
So two questions. First of all, in the
case of an alien invasion from outer
space, do you think the same math skills
are just as relevant today? And number
two, what would you do as an educator to
make sure that every girl has the
opportunity to excel in science as per
uh her aptitude and interests? Okay.
Firstly, in the case of an alien
invasion from outer space, would these
skills,
math skills, code breaking, pattern
recognition, memory, mathematics, etc.
Will those same skills be relevant
today, just as relevant today to counter
an alien invasion from outer space? You
see this codereing etc.
which was done during the second world
war using skills like pattern
recognition, memory, mathematics, etc.
This
was done to counter a human threat.
It was the allies against the axis. So
you had things like, you know, breaking
the Enigma code, etc., the Enigma
machine, which was a brilliant
cryptographic invention. But the Germans
and Island Touring and his team they
they they were able to to crack the code
and you had this program as well 16,000
girls. So all of these this code
breaking etc was done to counter human
threats to counter human intelligence.
It was human intelligence versus human
intelligence.
Right now, if you have an alien invasion
from outer space,
that presupposes that this alien invader
species is going to be capable of
traversing tremendous interstellar dis
distances and reaching our planet. Which
means that their technological
capabilities will be way higher than
ours, which means their intelligence is
going to be way higher than ours. Let's
say a sufficiently intelligent human
being has an IQ of let's say 150 then it
means that these aliens may have an IQ
of 400 500
and no amount
of pattern recognition memory or
mathematics or whatever is going to be
able to defeat those alien alien
invaders. So if there's an alien
invasion from outer space none of your
technology none of your mental
attributes intellectual attributes
technology whatever none of it will be
able to defeat the alien invaders. If
there's an alien invasion, if aliens
turn up
at our doorstep, having come from god
knows how many light years away, we're
done. We're cooked. There's nothing that
can that can save us. Unless the aliens
make some stupid mistakes like
like what they show in science fiction
movies. So that's number one. Number
two, what would I do as an educator to
make sure that every girl has the
opportunity to excel in science as per
aptitude and interest?
First thing I would have a level playing
field. Everybody gets the same
[clears throat] starting point.
Everybody is treated equally and
everybody is has is has to play by the
same rules. There is no selective
you know
selective rule rules for for different
rules for different people essentially.
So an education system has to be gender
agnostic. It doesn't matter what the
gender of the student is. Everybody has
to be treated the same. Everybody has to
be given the same opportunities and the
same rules to play by. That's number
one. Number two, the entire system has
to be based on merit. And number three,
the system should be such that it it it
seeks out and rewards talent and
aptitude and the capacity to work hard
etc. You do the things everybody will
excel. Not just girls but everybody
who's good enough will excel as per
their aptitude and interest. That's what
I would do. I would not do it
specifically for girls. I would do it
for everybody. I would treat everybody
the same because human beings have to be
treated the same irrespective of their
gender or color of skin or whatever
else. That's what I would do and
hopefully everybody thrives under that.
Okay, that brings me to the end of
today's questions to today's live
stream. I still have more questions that
I have selected but I won't be able to
take them today maybe in the next
session. Let's see what kind of live
chat we have. We have a whole bunch of
so we have Pravin ready is a new member.
Thank you so much Pravin G. Welcome to
membership. Thank you very much for
becoming a me member. Vssvs namaste.
Thank you very much. UMX
is talking about geopolitics.
We will discuss geopolitics and see
let me see the different super chats do
any of them have anything to do with
science vic manuscript manuscript is not
science it's history James is talking
about English
is talking about sudan
bal key today is
rishi's listen I don't mix
I do not mix religion and spirituality
with science. When we talk about the
concepts developed by our rishies,
we're talking about a certain period in
the historical development of science
that was several thousand years ago when
we did not have the understanding of
science that we have today.
So we can't
mix that with what we have today.
Initially
there was no clear understanding that
you have to keep science and
spirituality separate, science and
religion separate.
So you had people who did everything at
the same time. They talked about God and
science in the same breath. Science is
all about the material observable world
and observable phenomena and replicable
replicable phenomena. There is no
concept of spirit or morality or god or
demons or whatever in that.
So you can't mix these two things. I am
very clear about this.
So that's all I can say about this
matter.
There are all kinds of ancient concepts
that have elements of science in them.
And if India's civilization had not been
destroyed a thousand years ago
then we would have made tremendous
advances by now. But all we are doing
today is talking about what happened
thousands of years ago which is not
really part of this discussion today on
science.
Once again this is about spiritual
experiences which is not science.
MPS says firm paradox only indicates
there are no type two or type three
civilizations in Milky Way as their heat
signature would be recognizable but
there can be type8 civilizations at par
with us what's my POV
the firmy paradox asks simple asks a
simple question where is everybody
the Drake equation
talks about how many civilizations
intelligent civilizations there could be
in a specific galaxy based on a number
of criteria and parameters which we
don't know how to quantify.
Okay.
The as far as I understand the firmy
paradox doesn't say that you know type
so and so civilization. So you are
bringing in the permy paradox you're
bringing in the kardashev scale. You're
also bringing in somehow the drake
equation.
The way I see it, the firmy paradox asks
a simple question. Where is everybody?
You have 10 raised to 22 or 23 possible
planets stars in the observable
universe.
Let's say each star has at least one
planet. So you have 10 to 22 or 23 or 24
20 let's say 10 to 23
planets in the observable universe.
Let's say one in a million of these is
earthlike. So that's 10 to 17 or 16.
Let's say one of one out of a million of
these can
has developed life. So that's 10 raised
to 10. Let's say one out of a million of
these has earthlike int humanlike
intelligent life. That's 10 raised to
four.
So there should be at least 10,000
human level or higher civilizations in
the observable universe. That's I mean
if you are very skeptical it's still
10,000. So where is everybody? Why can't
we see anything? That's what the firmy
paradox asks. It doesn't talk about the
kardashev scale.
Right? That's how I see it.
Uh Bu says what's the actual color of
our sun? It's white.
But we see what do we see? We see
yellow, right? It's still white. Why is
it?
It's because
it's because of Earth's atmosphere.
It sucks out certain colors.
Okay, let me show you something. There
is something called the color wheel. The
HSL wheel.
Okay. Oh, what's that? One second. Give
me a second. Let me put this on the
screen. Okay. The color wheel. Let's
talk about two colors, blue and yellow.
They will be on the opposite ends of the
color wheel. Okay. Let's see
color wheel. See where is blue? Where is
yellow? Yellow. Opposite ends of the
color wheel.
So the sky
becomes blue, doesn't it?
And the sun appears yellow. If you add
blue and yellow together, you get white.
I mean, kind of like that.
So it's because of the atmosphere
absorbing certain wavelengths
from the white light of the sun, which
is why the sky becomes
blue.
and the sun appears yellow. But if you
go outside of the atmosphere and look at
the sun, maybe dim it a little bit,
[snorts] it'll it'll be white. So the
sun is a white the sun is a white star.
B says, why is the time considered to be
fourth dimension? Because you can call
it the first dimension if you like, but
it's because we consider the spatial
dimensions to be the three dimensions we
see. That's why time is called the
fourth dimension. You can give it
whatever title, whatever tag you want.
You can call it the zeroth dimension if
you like in your physics. It won't
affect the equations. So it's about why
have we given a certain title to this?
Why do we call this uh lime color? Why
don't we call this something else?
Doesn't matter. Works the same. Okay,
that brings me to the end of today's
session. I apologize to the the ones who
have taken super chats about topics that
are not connected to science. I will
only take science questions today. I
have repeatedly requested everybody if
this is a question about a certain topic
let's talk about that topic only
otherwise I'll break my rules and then
if there if if you have no rules then
you have no discipline in life and
everything goes to hell so I will only
discuss science today but that brings me
to the end of today's live stream I hope
it was something that gave you some
value maybe some better understanding of
the universe the world
and I look forward to seeing you in
tomorrow's live stream which is going to
about anything. So ask me anything
tomorrow in the super chat and I'll take
as many questions as possible tomorrow.
Until then, take care, keep learning,
keep asking questions and I will see you
tomorrow. Thank you everyone. Bye-bye.